<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Master Bakewells sea of absurdities concerning sprinkling calmely driven back / by Peter Chamberlen, 12 April, 1650.</title>
            <author>Chamberlen, Peter, 1601-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38996</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18204046</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18204046</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31641)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1629:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Master Bakewells sea of absurdities concerning sprinkling calmely driven back / by Peter Chamberlen, 12 April, 1650.</title>
                  <author>Chamberlen, Peter, 1601-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and are to be sold by Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19. --  Dippers plunged in a sea of absurdities.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107063:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MASTER</hi> BAKEWELLS SEA OF ABSURDITIES, <hi>CONCERNING</hi> SPRINKLING <hi>CALMELY</hi> Driven back by Peter Chamberlen. 12. <hi>April,</hi> 1650.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> And are to be ſold by <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle,</hi> at the West end of <hi>Pauls, 1650.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:107063:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107063:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Bakewells</hi> Sea of Abſurdities concerning <hi>SPRINKLING;</hi> calmely driven back by <hi>Peter Chamberlen, 12</hi> April <hi>1650.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>R. <hi>Bakewell,</hi> There was a Letter, with your name ſubſcribed, brought to <hi>Ely</hi> houſe the 24. of <hi>March,</hi> laſt (as I heard) and the ſame was afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto me; whereupon I ſent 4 times to your houſe, to have returned you an Anſwer, and either you were not at home (as the Meſſenger told me) or elſe you would not be at home: ſo that on the laſt Lords day, (7. <hi>April</hi> preſent) which you call the Sabbath or Palm Sunday, (which was the firſt time I was at <hi>Ely</hi> houſe ſince the Letter) I gave a publick Anſwer in the place where it was ſent. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you wrong your Friends, in poſſeſſing them, that you had defied <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and none durſt anſwer you, as your Preamble im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. Nor do you well to charge me with a promiſe I never made. For you neither could tell whether I made any promiſe, (you, nor your Meſſenger, not having ſpoken with me,) nor could you ſo much as know whether I had received your Letter, it neither being delivered unto me, nor to any in my preſence, nor yet left at my houſe. Nor truly, were you ſo civill as to ſend me a Copy of what you printed, and I had not known thereof, if another had not given me one.</p>
            <p>You ſay further, that you were requeſted by ſome Friends to publiſh your Letter. I partly believe you are but the <hi>Catts Paw,</hi> by your dabling in <hi>Greek</hi> (p. 6. &amp; laſt line) which probably you underſtood not; and by my Reverend Friend Mr. <hi>Downan's</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:107063:3"/>vouchſafing you an <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> and your own confeſſion here of your Friends Requeſt, yet I cannot but a little wonder at it. What? That your Miniſters ſhould allow a Lay-man to take upon him their Function! and to anſwer what they durſt not! They knew (perhaps) none ſo bold. —</p>
            <p>Well Mr. <hi>Bakewell,</hi> I ſhall not be ſo proud, as becauſe you may be cenſured by your own party, out of your Element, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which notion (perhaps) taking me, they permit you to do what you do:) therefore not to grant you an humble and loving Anſwer; however you are pleaſed to judge me proud of heart, and taking upon me the Title of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> &amp;c. Truly I am ſorry I cannot ſo behave my ſelf as to have prevented you from any ſuch raſh cenſure, and do but you teach me greater humility, wherein the truth of Chriſt may not ſuffer, and I ſhall be glad to learn of you that meekneſſe and humility, wherein you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt before me. Which nevertheleſs in this you ſeeme not to do, <hi>in preſuming to anſwer for</hi> Dr. Gouge, <hi>as ſuppoſing your ſelf the abler man, or abler then any of your ſprinkling Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt paſſe by many impertinencies, and touch upon the moſt material paſſages of the Letter, that I may avoid the words of rayling, and onely return an Anſwer in love.</p>
            <p>You except againſt my asking a queſtion of Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> becauſe he is ancient, Of whom ſhould men enquire but of the ancient <hi>ſhould not dayes ſpeak, and multitude of yeares teach wiſdome,</hi> Job 32.7. Of whom ſhould we enquire, but of thoſe that take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the Office? <hi>ſhould not the Prieſts lips preſerve know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</hi> Malach: 2.7. Why man, I ſent not to fight with Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> and ſo long the older the better: nor did I confine the queſtion to him, but that others were alſo lovingly intreated to his aſſiſtance. Yet having ſufficiently cenſured and chid me; you will not give me leave to ſtate mine own Queſtion; but pretend to know my meaning better then my ſelf. My Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, WHETHER THE SPRINKLING OF INFANTS BE OF GOD OR OF MAN? It is the ſame queſtion which Chriſt propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107063:3"/>to the Phariſees concerning the Baptiſme of <hi>John, Mat.</hi> 21.25. You have made a Queſtion of your own, WHETHER SPRINKLING THE BAPTIZED BE OF GOD OR MAN, BE THEY INFANTS OR OF FULLAGE? do you mean by Baptized, Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? as in your 6 page and laſt line you intimate. Then you Tautologize and will ſound thus in plain <hi>Engliſh, Whether ſprinkling the Sprinkled be of God or Man?</hi> or would you have thoſe that are baptized already, to be ſprinkled alſo? I pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with your Teachers a little before you either ſtate my Queſtion, or ſtate it in that manner. In the mean time I will ſuppoſe you ſpeak ſenſe, and that (at all adventures) you affirm that THE SPRINKLING OF INFANTS IS OF GOD AND NOT OF MANS INVENTION, which is quite contrary to what Dr. <hi>Gouge</hi> affirmed to ſome. For I have been informed by Mr. <hi>Edw. Barber,</hi> and have it under his hand ſince you printed your Letter, that at 2 ſeverall times, both upon his being ſent unto him by the Biſhops, and one <hi>Marke Whitlock,</hi> to be ſatisfied for taking the Oath <hi>ex officio:</hi> Dr. <hi>Gouge</hi> did acknowledge (not onely Sprinkling) but that baptizing of Infants was a tradition of the Church, and uſed it as one Argument to take that Oath: But to your Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Arg.</hi> You would prove that <hi>Sprinkling</hi> of Infants is of God, becauſe the Lord foretold that in the times of the Goſpel his <hi>people ſhould be ſprinkled with clean water. Ezek.</hi> 36.25. Mr. <hi>Bakewell,</hi> it had been well if you had deſired your Teachers to help you to make a Syllogiſme of it, whereof they that will undertake to diſpute, ought not to be ignorant; but becauſe you may chance not know what belongs to it, aske them whether by SPRINKLING here be meant BAPTISME? Or whether by CLEAN WATER, be meant ELEMENTARY WATER? Or whether by the words (UPON YOU, which you interpret his people) be meant LITTLE INFANTS? Or whether by THEN be meant the TIME OF THE GOSPEL with THE GENTILES, as you likewiſe render it? Or whether this SPRINKLING allude not rather to the SPRINKLING UNDER THE LAW, (<hi>Levit.</hi> 14.7. <hi>Numb,</hi> 8.7.)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107063:4"/>which they underſtood diſtinct from thoſe many Baptiſmes mentioned in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. which were amongſt them, and did not underſtand <hi>Johns</hi> or <hi>Chriſts</hi> Baptiſme, which as yet was not? And whether the PURE WATER be not rather the HOLY GHOST in the Language of our Saviour (<hi>John</hi> 7.39?) And whether the time THEN and the People You, be not rather the glorious times of the CALLING OF THE JEWES?</p>
            <p>I believe theſe miſtakes will rather put them upon a more ſtrict way of keeping the ſtaffe in their own hands, and not ſuffer Lay-ignorance though never ſo zealous, Talketive, or Devout, to betray their Cauſe. For when you or any elſe have ſaid all you can upon this place, IT IS A PROMISE OF WHAT GOD WILL DO, IT IS NOT A COMMAND OF WHAT MAN MUST DO.</p>
            <p>Then you ſay (Mr. <hi>Bakewell</hi>) that the water in BAPTISME is A SIGNE OF THE BLOOD OF CHRIST: but where doth the Scripture ſay ſo? They had under the Law, the SPRINKLING OF WATER. <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Numb.</hi> 8.7. diſtinct from the SPRINKLING OF BLOOD, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.22. and 29.21. and both diſtinct from their BATHES AND WASHINGS, <hi>Levit.</hi> 15.5.6.7.8.10.11.13.18.21.22.27. And 16.26.28. and 17.15.16. and <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.7.8.19. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.10. and 29.4. and 30.18.19. and 40.12.31. <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.27.28. <hi>Deut.</hi> 21, 6. and divers other places. And we have under the Goſpel BAPTISME diſtinct from the SUPPER OF THE LORD. And the Holy Ghoſt is punctuall, (<hi>John</hi> 19.34.) that there came out of the ſide of <hi>Jeſus</hi> both <hi>Water</hi> &amp; <hi>Blood.</hi> Now ſhould they have confounded the ſprinkling of water with that of blood, or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their waſhings, or one with the other under the Law, they could not but have neglected a great part of thoſe Rights and Ceremonies wherein they were to be ſo exact: And if we alſo ſhould confound thoſe few Commands which our Saviour leſt us under the Goſpel, we ſhould ſoone arrive to that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Babel which is ſo rife in theſe dayes amongſt many who ſuppoſe themſelves ſpiritual. Forbeare therefore ſo boldly to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107063:4"/>affirme or inferre that the water in Baptiſme is called in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. <hi>The blood of ſprinkling.</hi> But if you will needes finde Baptiſme in that Text, find it in our <hi>coming to Jeſus the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the new Covenant,</hi> from the which the <hi>Blood of ſprinkling</hi> is diſtinguiſhed by a conjunction Copulative (AND). That alſo of the 10. of <hi>Heb.</hi> 22. muſt be kept from confuſion, and then it comprehends the 2 compleat parts of Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The work and promiſe of God in theſe words. <hi>Our hearts ſprinckled from an evill Conſcience,</hi> and the work and obedience of men in theſe words. <hi>Our Bodies waſhed with pure water.</hi> For IT IS NOT THE WORK OF MAN TO SPRINKLE THE HEART, NOR IS IT THE WORK OF GOD TO WASH THE BODY. 2. GODS SPRINKLING IS EQUIVALENT TO MANS WASHING, In which ſenſe the phraſe is uſed of GODS FINGER, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.19.31.18. And theſe two parts are diſtinctly held forth in many places, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. <hi>Luke</hi> 3. <hi>I baptize with water, but he ſhall baptize with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And <hi>Act</hi> 1.5. <hi>John bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with water, but ye ſhall be baptized with the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> So <hi>Act</hi> 2.38. <hi>Repent and be baptized, and ye ſhall receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> If either of theſe be wanting, Baptiſme is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. For Chriſt himſelf, <hi>who had not the ſpirit by meaſure, must be baptized to fulfill all righteouſneſſe</hi> (<hi>Mat:</hi> 3.) <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> by <hi>Cornelius</hi> his Companies receiving the HOLY GHOST, judgeth them <hi>thereby fit to be baptized with water: Act</hi> 10. <hi>Who can forbid water that theſe ſhould not be baptized, who have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we? And he commvn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to be baptized.</hi> And on the other ſide without <hi>fruits worthy of Repentance,</hi> the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſhall not be admitted to the BAPTISME OF WATER. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7.8.) Nor probably the Eunuch, unleſſe he had BELIEVED WITH ALL HIS HEART. <hi>Act</hi> 8.37. <hi>For it is not the outward waſhing away the filth of the fleſh, but the inward anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your ſecond Argument or Article with the latter end of the firſt, layes down a Rule of Similitude between the ſigne (or Sacrament, in your phraſe) and the thing ſignified. Conſider your own Rule, with SPRINKLING OF A CHILDES FACE,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107063:5"/>(which is a Ceremony but lately allowed, by the late <hi>Directory,</hi> and was not allowed (though practiſed) by the <hi>Book of Common Prayer.</hi> Conſider I pray you, whether by your Rule you do not make a <hi>Face-Christian,</hi> yea a <hi>ſpecled face-Chriſtian,</hi> your SPRINK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING being onely on the FACE, and that but <hi>here</hi> and <hi>there</hi> in DROPS; but if you allow BAPTISME to ſignifie the WASHING AWAY OF SIN, as all <hi>Catechiſmes</hi> imply, would you onely waſh away the FACE and OUTWARD APPEARANCES OF SIN, to make an <hi>Outſide-Phariſee-Chriſtian?</hi> or would you have ALL SIN, even the <hi>whole body of Sin waſhed away?</hi> Therefore the <hi>waſhing of the whole Body,</hi> as was appointed by the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> and was the COMMAND and PRACTISE of CHRIST and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POSTIES, and of thoſe learned men whom they commonly call <hi>FATHERS,</hi> is <hi>the right way of adminiſtring the Sacrament,</hi> and not a new-invented way of <hi>SPRINKLING,</hi> which (though practiſed) was <hi>NEVER COMMANDED TILL OF LATE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compare it alſo with thoſe other <hi>REPRESENTATIONS IN BAPTISME,</hi> would you have the Baptiſme of the HOLY GHOST to be but in <hi>DROPS,</hi> and that but in APPEARANCE, on the FACE, or but one <hi>PART?</hi> Or would you be <hi>FILLED</hi> ſo as to have <hi>Rivers of living water flow out of your Belly? John</hi> 7.39. Would you have your FACE onely BURIED WITH CHRIST IN BAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISME, or have your FACE onely BAPTIZED INTO HIS DEATH, and have onely your <hi>FACE</hi> to <hi>RISE WITH HIM,</hi> or have one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an <hi>Outſide-ſhew of Death to Sin, and Reſurrection to life in Chriſt?</hi> (<hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.34. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Or would you make <hi>CHRIST</hi> only a <hi>VISARD FOR YOUR FACE,</hi> to <hi>PUT HIM</hi> only <hi>ON UPON YOUR FACE?</hi> (<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.) Lay your hand upon your heart, and conſider ſeriouſly theſe things.</p>
            <p>Then you inſiſt upon the <hi>VISIBILITY OF THE SIGNE OF THE BAPTIZED, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt, conſider your own Practice. Do <hi>INFANTS SEE THE WATER</hi> wherewith they are ſprinkled? Are their <hi>EYES</hi> commonly <hi>OPEN</hi> or <hi>SHUT?</hi> Do any pluck them open? yea, if they were open, would not nature teach them to ſhut them when they felt the drops of water upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107063:5"/>them? Or if they open their eyes, know they what water is, or what it meanes? Secondly, Whether is a <hi>Baſon of Water,</hi> or a <hi>River</hi> moſt viſible? Is not this like the old Woman that could ſee the needle, but not the Barne? Thirdly, whereas you ſay that he who is plunged doth not <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>Signe,</hi> if you mean <hi>WATER,</hi> He doth not onely <hi>ſee</hi> it but <hi>feele</hi> it, and if you mean the <hi>Waſhing</hi> and <hi>Clenſing</hi> of <hi>his Body,</hi> ſurely they are more likely to ſee their Bodies clenſed that go into a <hi>RIVER,</hi> and afterwards drie themſelves and wipe away the filth, then they that onely have their <hi>Face Sprinkled,</hi> which they cannot ſee without a <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> (a thing of no uſe to New borne Infants.) And whereas you ſay that they cannot <hi>heare</hi> what is ſaid, no more do <hi>Infants,</hi> nor do they <hi>underſtand</hi> if they <hi>hear</hi> the words; but the baptized according to the Scriptures do both heare the words and <hi>know</hi> them before they are plunged, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though pronouncing the <hi>WORDS,</hi> do not the work, but the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> of being Baptized into the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Your third <hi>Article</hi> ſaith, that many were <hi>Baptized in their houſes,</hi> and you inſtance in <hi>Paul, Cornelius,</hi> and the Jaylor, for whom you quote <hi>Act</hi> 9.17.18. &amp; 16.25.48. You do ill (Mr. <hi>Bakewell</hi>) to father ſo many untruths in print upon the Scriptures. The Scriptures ſay <hi>NOT</hi> that <hi>PAUL</hi> was <hi>BAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIZED</hi> in the <hi>HOUSE:</hi> but that <hi>Ananias entred into the Houſe,</hi> and afterwards when the ſcales were fallen from his eyes, he <hi>aroſe</hi> and was <hi>Baptized</hi> without ſaying he was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized either in a Tub or Pond, (according to your roving lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,) or in a River: or that he was Baptized without Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as the Drie-waſhing Book of the Doctrine of Baptiſmes will inferre. You may likewiſe read it again in <hi>Act</hi> 22.16. <hi>Paul</hi> was not to ſit ſtill to be ſprinkled; but, <hi>now up, why tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt thou? ariſe and be Baptized, and waſh away thy ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Act</hi> 10. <hi>Peter</hi> after having reaſoned the buſineſs about <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> and thoſe with him, <hi>who can forbid water, &amp;c?</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to be <hi>Baptized,</hi> but it is <hi>not</hi> ſaid <hi>where,</hi> nor <hi>by whom.</hi> And if you allow any water to be uſed (as is expreſſed) you muſt either ſuppoſe it carried up and down with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107063:6"/>in <hi>Aqua-vitae-Bottles,</hi> or <hi>Roſe-water-Bottles,</hi> to daſh them in the face as ſoone as they had been but taken confeſſing of Chriſt, or that whereſoever they came, they either found or called for a Baſon of water in the firſt place (which we do not read they did) or elſe <hi>the ſame time that would ſerve to fetch water and bring it back, might ſerve them to go to the water.</hi> And in the 16. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> I perceive you do not ſo much as read the 30. verſe, elſe you would never have put in print that the Jaylor and all his were <hi>baptized in the Priſon, quite contrary to the Text,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>that the Jaylor came trembling, and fell down before Paul and Silas, and brought them out,</hi> at leaſt out of the inner Priſon, <hi>before it is ſaid</hi> that he asked <hi>what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> and in the 33. verſe, <hi>he took them the ſame houre of the night, and waſhed their ſtripes and was Baptized, he and all his ſtraightway, before</hi> it is ſaid that <hi>he brought them into his houſe, &amp;c.</hi> Nor is it probable that they were <hi>Baptized with water, and the blood</hi> of the <hi>Stripes</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Silas. Abſurdities muct not be put upon the Scriptures, but the main being expreſſed, the rest ought to be underſtood, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully expreſſed in other places.</hi> All the following Queſtions therefore denote your extream ignorance both in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; in that Ordinance. And your great partiality appears in that you asked not the ſame abſurd queſtions about the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Silas,</hi> &amp; the Baptiſm of the Jaylor &amp; his houſhold. As what Veſſel? Who ſhould fetch it? How often emptyed? Did <hi>Paul</hi> ſtand in a Veſſell? How many times went he in? or vvent he in at all? Wherefore all theſe Abſurdities cannot but ſtick faſt in your weak Imagination, till they be all diſſolved in a RIVER, or SUFFICIENT QUANTITY OF WATFR.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the 4. place, you ſay the SACRAMENT muſt be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred WHERE THE WORD IS PREACHED, becauſe that <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. You ſay it is, Preach and Baptize. Here you alſo play the falſe Prophet in your falſe Interpretation and Repetition. For the word is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Preach</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Diſcipline</hi> or make Diſciples, nor is it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>baptize</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>baptizing much leſſe</hi> doth the Text
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107063:6"/>either ſay or inferre that <hi>they muſt baptize in the ſame place where they preach: John Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Diſciples</hi> went up and down preaching the Goſpel in the WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERNES, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1. and <hi>about all Galilee, Mat.</hi> 4.24. and up in a MOUNTAIN. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.1. &amp; 10.7. &amp; 27. &amp; 11.1. and in a CHARIOT. <hi>Act</hi> 8.4.31. &amp; 35. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they BAPTIZED in JORDAN. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.5. <hi>John</hi> 3.22. in AENON. <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Upon the ſame ſcore of ignorance you have the like troubled fancy as in the 3. Article, about a Rivers banck, or half way in the River, or 2 Perſons at leaſt to adminiſter the Ordinance, from all which abſurdities you ſprinkle your ſelf with Holy water, and reſt in a contented ignorance.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Againſt ſuppoſed NAKEDNES you alleadge MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DESTY, and againſt ClOTHING you would not have them ſit DUNG-WET at meat, and againſt a <hi>Partiall Cloathing</hi> you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge <hi>Aarons Briches,</hi> with many other weak things, even an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the very readding. For by this you allow not <hi>Jeſus,</hi> nor the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> nor all the reſt to be <hi>nor Naked, nor Cloathed, nor half Naked and half Cloathed.</hi> And were your modeſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions true, what think you of CIRCUMCISION? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps when you duly weigh theſe things, and deny your ſelf-conceits and ſtrange Imaginations, to ſubmit them to the Truths of Scripture, your zeal may be converted into know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which truly is my Prayer for you. For I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you write not in malice to me, though in hard cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Seventhly, Mr. <hi>Bakewell,</hi> you affirm another untruth of the Scriptures for want of knowledge of the Tongues, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the error of the Tranſlator. <hi>Mark</hi> 3.11. where <hi>John</hi> is made to ſay I baptize <hi>with Water,</hi> and not <hi>in</hi> water, and ſay you, the Scripture alwayes ſaith <hi>with</hi> water. Now if you your ſelf were ſuch a <hi>Grecian,</hi> as to be Author ſufficient for the <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as you undertake in the laſt line of the 6. page, you might alſo be credited here, having the tranſlation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107063:7"/>on your ſide, which there you have not: but becauſe I believe you are not, but ſpeak by roat as you are taught, I pray aske your Teachers (who know the Tongues,) and they will tell you, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth <hi>in water,</hi> and not <hi>with water.</hi> And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>with the waſhing of water in the word.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. hath neither <hi>in</hi> nor <hi>with,</hi> onely the <hi>Dative</hi> Caſe, which our language will not render with any propriety. And truly it were well, if thoſe errors which are cauſed for want of a more exact Tranſlation, were taken away by a new Tranſlation. And till you are able to be an Interpreter, it is good to be ſober in making your own Concluſion upon matter of Interpretation; but yield the place to thoſe that are better able, and better gifted: till when, I muſt leave you in the midſt of all your abſurdities which you have framed and affirmed, and not I, nor any one as I know but your ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Eighthly, you began with a hard word <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> and you ſhould do wel to know what that word meanes, and how to uſe it, and to whom it belongs, before you undertake to condemn any under that notion. And when you underſtand the true ſignification of Baptiſme, you will not <hi>exact Brick, and allow no ſtraw,</hi> you will not bid one <hi>cut meat without a knife,</hi> you will not expect that men ſhould be <hi>baptized, and not ſuffer them to come into the water.</hi> And for your <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> of ſaying that Infants are <hi>under</hi> water for being <hi>lower</hi> then that handfull of water held by your Miniſters in ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, it is too ridiculous, as divers other paſſages, to be either anſwered at all, or at all ſeriouſly anſwered: nor would your Miniſters have pleaded that for an <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Laſtly, you promiſe to ſhew that <hi>Sprinkling one part</hi> of the Body is <hi>ſufficient:</hi> but you pull in your Arguments with Ropes of Sand.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One DROP of water is as truly water as the whole <hi>Ocean;</hi> what followes? Therefere one DROP of water is as SUFFICI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENT as the whole OCEAN! For what? To feede <hi>Whales?</hi> To
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107063:7"/>beare great Ships? To vvater the Earth? to vvaſh and bath? no nor to ſprinkle neither. Or vvhat vvould you have to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? That as one drop of vvater is vvater as vvell as the vvhole Ocean, ſo is one part of the body a Body, as vvell as the vvhole Body? This concludes nothing to your purpoſe. Or that as one drop of vvater is vvaetr as vvell as the vvhole Ocean; ſo if one part of the body be ſprinkled all the body is ſprinkled. The ſimilitude vvil not hold nor follow: but trie the practiſe of it vvhen your face is foule, vvaſh your feet, and ſee vvhether your face vvill be any vvhit the cleaner.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſay there is <hi>no meaſure of water preſcribed,</hi> onely it muſt be vvater. No more there is <hi>for your Bread,</hi> yet one drop vvill not ſuffize to make Dowe: nor vvill one drop ſerve to vvaſh your hands or feet, vvhen you go to knead it: and it vvere ridiculous for the Apoſtle to mention that <hi>John</hi> vvas bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing in <hi>Aenon,</hi> BECAUSE THERE WAS MUCH WATER THERE, if one drop vvould have ſerved the turne; but ſo there be enough it is no matter vvhether it be in <hi>Jordan</hi> or <hi>Aenon,</hi> or the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe. <hi>Act</hi> 8. or the River vvithout the City of <hi>Philippi. Act.</hi> 16.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You ſay (to as little purpoſe) that the baptized may be under one drop as vvell as under a Tunne; ſo he may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Tunne as vvell as one drop, and vve are daily under more in the Cloudes: but vvhat vvould you inferre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? That a man may be buried and plunged, or drowned vvith one drop, or by being under one drop, as vvell as by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under a Tunne? He may indeed be as drie under a Tunne as under one drop, ſo the Veſſell leake not: in the ſenſe you mentioned laſt of the Childs being under the Miniſters handfull of vvater, but not ſo ſoone buried or plunged vvith one drop as vvith a Tunne of vvater; and if the Sextone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded but one graine of earth upon each body that vvere to be buried, I believe each Noſtril vvould ſoon complain there vvere not ſufficient.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107063:8"/>
            <p>But 4. you as deſperately attempt to clear this by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Peter</hi> about the waſhing of his Feet. <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.8. Read on to the 10. verſe. He that is <hi>Waſhed</hi> (ſaith he) or he that is <hi>already Baptized, needeth not ſave to cleanſe or waſh his feete, &amp;c:</hi> This ſhewes (ſay you, from the 8. verſe inſtancing, <hi>in me</hi> for <hi>with me,</hi> as almoſt in all the Scriptures you quote, you miſtake ſomewhat) this ſhewes that waſhing was ſacramentall. If you mean it is a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> why do you not ſo <hi>practiſe it?</hi> If it be the <hi>Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> why do not your <hi>Ministers</hi> waſh the <hi>feet of Infants</hi> as <hi>Chriſt did his Diſciples,</hi> rather then <hi>ſprinkle the face</hi> onely, which <hi>Chriſt never did?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you have ſpoken your laſt, you come with 3. <hi>OBIECTIONS</hi> for plunging, from <hi>Act</hi> 8.38. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. To the firſt you anſwer, that <hi>every Pit or River</hi> in thoſe hot Countries were <hi>not alwayes brim-full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Be it ſo Therefore every <hi>Pit</hi> (which you make a <hi>Synonyma</hi> to a <hi>River</hi>) was not choſen: but the chief <hi>River Jordan,</hi> and <hi>Aenon,</hi> becauſe there was much water. You ſay they might go into the <hi>Pit,</hi> and not go into the water. The Lord deliver us from the <hi>Pit</hi> where there is no water (<hi>Jer.</hi> 39.6. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11.) but the Text anſwers your Cavel, (if you would at all heed what the word ſaith) that in the Baptiſme of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and the Eunuch, where the <hi>manner of Baptizing</hi> is particularly mentioned, they <hi>went both down into the water, and they came up out of the water,</hi> not into the Pit, and out of the Pit. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.9.10. <hi>Act</hi> 8.39.</p>
            <p>To the 2. <hi>you affirme,</hi> that the <hi>Greek</hi> word (which I ſuppoſe you can neither write nor read, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Infinitive</hi>) doth ſignifie as well to SPRINKLE as to PLUNGE, whereas all the Schollers in <hi>Europe</hi> cannot finde it ſo uſed in any <hi>Greek</hi> Author, nor others; but of late ſome <hi>Latine</hi> Authors (from the practiſe) have raſhly printed what you here affirme. Which if it ſhould be granted, and your Teſtament ſo interpreted, heare a little your own Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1. <hi>In thoſe dayes came John the</hi> SPRINKLER,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107063:8"/>
               <hi>preaching in the Wildernes of Jordan. Then went out to him Jeruſalem and all Judea, and all the Region round about Jordan, and were</hi> SPRINKLED <hi>of him in Jordan the River. Mark</hi> 1.5. <hi>John</hi> 3.22. <hi>After theſe things came Jeſus and his Diſciples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land of Judea, and there he tarried with them, and</hi> SPRINKLED, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. <hi>And John alſo was</hi> SPRINKLING <hi>in Aenon,</hi> BECAUSE <hi>there was</hi> MUCH WATER <hi>there, and they came and were</hi> SPRINKLED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mark</hi> 1.19. <hi>And it came to paſſe in thoſe dayes, that Jeſus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was</hi> SPRINKLED <hi>of John (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) into Jordan, verſe</hi> 10. <hi>And ſtraightway coming up ut of the water,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Act</hi> 8.30. <hi>And they went down both into the water; both Philip and the Eunuch, and he</hi> SPRINKLED <hi>him. verſe</hi> 39. <hi>And when they came out of the Water, the Spirit caught away Philip. So Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>As many as have been</hi> SPRINKLED <hi>into Chriſt have put on Chriſt, and Col.</hi> 2.12. BURIED <hi>with him in</hi> SPRINKLING; <hi>wherein alſo ye are riſen with him;</hi> But I confeſſe, this ſort of bettering the Tranſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhall not like in my Bible.</p>
            <p>Yet not content with all theſe Abſurdities, you ſay you might adde more of <hi>plunging in water,</hi> and <hi>danger of lives,</hi> and <hi>you condemn men of murther</hi> for having plunged in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>yet name none</hi> that were murthered, nor executed for that murther, nor is there any proof ſave <hi>you own Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Imagination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To avoid the hardſhip of Winter, the <hi>Common-prayer-Book</hi> will tell you in the preamble, that <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide</hi> were therefore appointed by the Ancients for fit times of Baptiſme. And the <hi>Winter-Baptizing</hi> of Children in <hi>Wales,</hi> will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently teſtifie that you foiſt in your own untruths, by the ſtrength of your own diſtracted Imagination.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to the 3 <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. you would take a great advantage, becauſe there is <hi>no mention of water,</hi> and will make it a drie Baptiſme. When you bid your man <hi>waſh your Cup,</hi> or <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> unles you bid him <hi>do it with water,</hi> doth it ſignifie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107063:9"/>nothing? But let him that is diligent read the Texts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8. and ſatisfie themſelves.</p>
            <p>To as little purpoſe do you bring in all the other places of Scripture, and therefore I ſhall trouble my ſelf no futrher in the particulars of them. Nor do I intend further to be at Charges of printing a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to every one that Scribles, after having ſpent and loſt ſo much for the publick, and repayed with ſo much injuſtice and ingratitude. Nor will I meddle at preſent with the lawfullneſle or unlawfulneſſe of your Miniſtry, which you bring in by head and ſhoulders.</p>
            <p>Therefore you may well perceive by my patience in anſwering your weak <hi>Arguments,</hi> and by my waving all your words of provocation and cenſure, as of <hi>Pride,</hi> like <hi>Tyrus, Queſtions of ſtrife, Janglings, that I know nothing</hi> (P. 2.) <hi>Popiſh Pilgrimage,</hi> (P. 4.) <hi>to abide in the Aſſe or with the Aſſe.</hi> (P. 8.) <hi>and his invention who was a murtherer.</hi> (P. 7.) <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> (P. 6.) <hi>mad and drunk.</hi> (P. 3.) <hi>Dippers plunged in a Sea of Abſurdities</hi> (in the Title.) <hi>Renouncing of Baptiſme, denying of God, Devills, Heaven, Hell, Grace, Glory, and the like;</hi> that I am not al ogether ſo proud as you cenſured me, but that I deſire in meekneſs and lowlineſſe of Spirit to win you and all of your opinion (not to mine, but) to the truths of God, which the Lord grant through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printers_notice">
            <p>
               <hi>The late coming forth of this Impreſſion is to be amongſt the Errata of the Printer: He that deſires to be ſatisfied of the point, may read the Scriptures, and the Diſputes between Mr.</hi> Denne <hi>and Mr.</hi> Tombes, <hi>Dr.</hi> Featly <hi>and Mr.</hi> Marſhall. <hi>And Mr.</hi> Blackwells <hi>ſtorming of</hi> Antichriſt. <hi>And Mr.</hi> Laurence <hi>his Treatiſe of</hi> Baptiſe. <hi>Or the Book entituled the Vanity of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Baptiſmes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But they that are like Gallie</hi> (<hi>Act</hi> 14.15.16.17.18.) <hi>may let all alone.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
